Guide to the Jill Over Papers, 1966-2011 RL.00985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jill Over papers
1966-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Over, Jill
RL.00985
6.5 Linear Feet
Feminist and social activist: involved in anti-war movement, abortion rights campaigns, youth and adolescent sex education, and pro-democracy movements in Latin America and Africa. Collection includes publications and research files related to human rights, social justice activism, and peace in Latin America and the United States; as well as ephemera, pamphlets, periodicals, and clippings related to youth liberation, sex education, reproductive health, and feminism, especially during the 1970s and 1980s. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture and the Human Rights Archive (Duke University).
3500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jill Over Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Biographical Note
Jill Over (b. 1945, Dayton, Ohio) has been an activist and feminist since college. Following her year at the University of Ghana and a two-month Study Seminar in ten African countries in 1965-1966, she became an ardent supporter of African liberation movements. In the 1970s in Connecticut, she was active in the anti-war (Vietnam), women's rights, abortion rights, and anti-nuclear movements. In the pre-Roe vs. Wade years, she worked with an underground movement for women seeking safe abortions. After earning a graduate degree in social work at the University of Connecticut in 1976, she moved to Durham, North Carolina, and worked in hospitals, women's clinics, social services, and schools. Her activities as a school social worker included the development of a human sexuality curriculum for elementary school children and a Drive-A-Teen program for high school students. She also participated in community groups focused on adolescent issues. In the 1980s, her activism centered on community-based groups in support of self-determination for Nicaragua, El Salvador, Guatemala, and Honduras. As the Chapter Coordinator of Physicians for Social Responsibility in the 1990s, a main issue was the hazards of low-level radioactive waste.
Collection Overview
Collection includes publications and research files related to human rights, social justice activism, and peace in Latin America and the United States; as well as ephemera, pamphlets, periodicals, and clippings related to youth liberation, sex education, reproductive health, and feminism, primarily dating from the 1970s and 1980s.
Feminism; Human Rights; Women's rights; Latin America -- Human rights -- 20th century; Social justice; Latin America -- Peace; Sex instruction -- United States; Abortion -- United States; Over, Jill; Over, Jill
- Subject and Research Files, 1966-2011, 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Collection includes publications and research files related to human rights, social justice activism, and peace in Latin America and USA; as well as ephemera, pamphlets, periodicals, and clippings related to youth liberation, sex education, reproductive health, and feminism, especially during the 1970s and 1980s.
  - Latin America, 1974-1996, 2 boxes
    - Periodicals and Books
      - Report on Guatemala (NISGUA), 1983-1984, 4 issues (Box 1)
      - Guatemala (NACLA), 1974 (Box 1)
      - Honduras Update (Honduras Information Center), 1983-1987, 11 issues (Box 1)
      - Hoyt, Katherine: 30 Years of Memories: Dictatorship, Revolution, and Nicaraguan Solidarity (Nicaraguan Network Education Fund), 1996 (Box 1)
      - Nicaragua Network News, 1987-1988, 6 issues (Box 1)
      - Close-Up (Coalition for a New Foreign Policy), 1986-1987, 6 issues (Box 1)
    - Articles
      - Central America articles, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
      - El Salvador articles, 1980-1995 (Box 1)
      - Guatemala articles, 1980-1985 (Box 1)
      - Honduras articles, 1980-1985 (Box 1)
      - Nicaragua articles, 1980-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Veterans Peace Convoy to Nicaragua, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
      - Various Publications about the Americas, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
      - ALERT (CISPES, El Salvador), 1983-1991, 20 issues (Box 4)
  - Social Justice, Peace and Human Rights, 1966-1995, 2 boxes
    - Periodicals and Handbooks
      - Science for the People, 1975-1989, 48 issues (Box 1)
        - 1975 - v.7, 2 issues, July, November (Box 1)
        - 1976 - v.8, 2 issues, Jan., September/October (Box 1)
        - 1977 - v.9, 2 issues, January/February, May/June (Box 1)
        - 1978 - v.10, 3 issues, January/February, September/October, November/December (Box 1)
        - 1979 - v.11, all 6 issues (Box 1)
        - 1980 - v.12, all 6 issues (Box 1)
        - 1981 - v.13, 5 issues (missing September/October) (Box 1)
        - 1982 - v.14, all 6 issues (Box 1)
        - 1983 - v.15, 4 issues (missing March/April, November/December) (Box 1)
        - 1984 - v.16, 5 issues (missing October/November) (Box 1)
        - 1985 - v.17, 4 issues (1 is double issue, missing October/November) (Box 1)
        - 1986 - none (Box 1)
        - 1987 - v.19, 1 issue, September/October (Box 1)
        - 1988 - none (Box 1)
        - 1989 - v.21, 1 issue, January/February (Box 1)
      - Africa News, 1977-1993 (15 issues) (Box 1)
      - Convergence and Contragate Alert (The Christic Institute), 1987-1992 (Box 1)
      - The New Democrat, 1985-1986, 2 issues (Box 1)
      - The Expert Red, Handbook for American Revolutionaries, 1984-1985, 3 issues (Box 1)
      - The People's Advocate (Southern Justice Institute), 1990-1992, 5 issues (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous Publications, 1975-1988 (Box 2)
    - Individual Issues and Articles
      - Africa news clippings, 1971-1974 (Box 2)
      - Africa News Service, 1977-1987 (Box 2)
      - Bob Sheldon, death, 1991 (Box 2)
      - Durham Action Committee for Central America (DACCA) and Durham Alliance in Solidarity with Central America (DASCA), 1980-1990 (Box 2)
      - General Electric boycott, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
      - Greensboro Massacre news clippings, 1979-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Greensboro Justice Fund and Greensboro Civil Rights Fund letters and newsletters, 1980-1985 (Box 2)
      - Articles, reports and commemorations, 1980-1985 (Box 2)
      - Karen Silkwood, 1980-1987 (Box 2)
      - Ku Klux Klan, 1980-1993 (Box 2)
      - Leonard Peltier, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
      - Medical Committee for Human Rights (MCHR) (Durham), 1977 and undated (Box 2)
      - North Carolina Federation for Progress, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Physicians for Social Responsibility (PSR), 1988-1993 (Box 2)
      - Rosenberg/Sobell case, 1983 (Box 2)
      - Southern Africa, 1966-1972 (Box 2)
      - Unions at Duke University, 1979-1982 (Box 2)
      - Union of Concerned Scientists, 1980-1992 (Box 2)
      - War Resistor's League (WRL), 1977-1987 (Box 2)
      - Whole Foods (Wellspring Grocery takeover), 1991 (Box 2)
      - Yolanda Huet-Vaughn, 1991-1995 (Box 2)
  - Feminism, 1975-1996, 1 box
    - Article reprints, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Clippings from various publications, 1980-1996 (Box 2)
    - Ephemera, 1980-1985 (Box 2)
    - Pamphlets, 1975-1980 (Box 2)
    - Periodical issues, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Women: Literature, books, archives, 1976-1992 (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Holly Near, Redwood Records, Cultural and Educational Fund, 1979-1991 (Box 2)
  - Sex Education/Reproductive Health, 1968-2009, 2 boxes
    - Pamphlets, 1968-1980, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Teaching Materials, 1985-1987 and undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Abortion, 1980-1994 (Box 3)
    - Chamber of Commerce Ad Hoc Committee on Sexuality, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Women's Health: toxic shock, hormone RT, mammograms, 1980-2009 (Box 3)
  - Youth Liberation, 1978-2011, 1 box
    - Articles and Periodical Issues, 1981-1993 (Box 3)
    - Pamphlets, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
    - Publications about/for children, 1980-1986 (Box 3)
    - Publications about youth, adolescence, human growth, 1981-2011 (Box 3)
  - Oversize Materials, undated, 1 folder
    - Free the Wilmington 10 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Comrade Jim Waller, Martyr, Central Committee Member, Communist Workers Party, USA (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Comrade Sandy Smith, Martyr, Communist Workers Party, USA (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Comrade Michael Nathan, Martyr, Communist Workers Party, USA (Oversize-folder 1)